hello everyone um I just wanted to jump
on before the podcast starts just to
give you a prior warning that
unfortunately for a reason that I
haven't been able to discern Ronnie's
video is a little jumpy it's not
particularly smooth so you would notice
that anyway but I wanted to yep give you
a heads up obviously if you find it too
much don't watch the video but it's a
wonderful conversation so please don't
miss out uh and yeah you'll enjoy
whether you're watching it or listening
to it but yeah just wanted to to let you
know okay enjoy the
episode hello everyone and welcome back
to active inference insights I'm your
host as always darus parvey Wayne and
today I'm thrilled to be able to speak
to Ronald sladkey Ronnie is a cognitive
neuroscientist at the University of
Vienna Austria where he teaches courses
on cognitive science and predictive
processing his research focuses on the
amydala as well as emotion processing
and social cognition in the human brain
brain in addition to this he has been
part of a team developing realtime fmri
or functional magnetic resonance imaging
where people can learn to regulate their
own brain States while they are inside
the MRI scanner Ronnie welcome to the
show thank you so much for joining me
it's it's uh really exciting to have a
proper full fully fledged neuroscientist
on the show thank you it's really a
pleasure to be here so you you know part
of the reason why I wanted to have you
on is because you wrote this fascinating
paper grounding what you called the
amigdala complex in active inference uh
and I have plenty of questions about
that but before we actually go there I
thought an interesting starting point is
that you one very rarely meets people
who teach active inference and
predictive
processing um at least in my experience
within universities it's kind of like oh
there's this little thing that started
emerging and there are these kind of um
esoteric people studying but let's not
worry too much about that let's talk
about reinforcement learning or or
something a little bit more accepted
what's the reception being like teaching
predictive processing and active
inference um within your courses okay
that's that's a good question I mean I
think uh it only works uh because of the
master program that we have in Vienna so
we have an inter disciplinary master
program in cognitive science so I was
one of the first students actually study
this back in 2007 I think and so it's
located at the philosophy faculty
but it's interdisciplinary so we have
some kind of core seminars and then are
sent out to all the different institutes
say Neuroscience or behavioral biology
and we just take lectures there and do
our exams there and then come back to
the philosophy uh department and then
try to integrate everything we've heard
so there has always been this kind of
curiosity to say okay um we take up
students coming from different
backgrounds with different Bachelor
degrees so my bachelor is in was in
computer science um um and then we
basically want them to reflect on the
paradigms that they are
using so um back then uh the most recent
Paradigm was actually for E cognition
and and from there we kind of moved on
and so they asked me to uh teach now the
uh new trends in cognitive science uh um
um seminar and this was then about
predictive processing fantastic what um
around what year did they ask you to do
that so I mean I started with let's say
predictive processing in about 2009 or
something so actually was already
inspired early on after reading uh on
intelligence by Jeff Hawkins so I
stumbled on this book it was yeah a
little bit outside the typical Canon on
incognitive science but I stumbled on it
and I thought this idea very interesting
this idea of predictive coding and um
then yeah um the interest actually grew
in 2009 2010 and uh I was kind of
familiar with the early uh writings of
Carl Christen and from there on I
started to tell people hey guys you know
this is I think the next big Paradigm
and at some point I was able to convince
people also in Vienna to give me a
course on this topic
and it grew from there and every year
I've got two 25 new students and teach
them processing that's fantastic uh
that's super cool I mean I was at UCL
and again I'm not going to bad mouth UCL
they gave me a very good education this
was for my
masters uh as I said interestingly
although Carl's there and Chris fiff and
all of these people who are very seminal
in the creation of active inference very
little so I think that's really
encouraging that you guys are are
teaching it um that said obviously there
are some fantastic resources out there
online whether it's the textbook whether
it's uh something like Ryan Smith's ch
tutorial IE but that's how have you seen
the I'm curious about how you've seen
the kind of transformation in the
acceptance of active inference as an
idea because I presume back in sort of
2009 2010 when people were still talking
about feed forward
models um you know it was probably
frowned upon that the brain was
constructing its experience and there
was a so-called controlled hallucination
going on so how you know what was that
process like of people coming on coming
on side oh absolutely I mean I was
somehow caught between the lines so I
mean I was coming from my cognitive
Science Background to say okay let's um
you know uh get over with behaviorism
and cognitivism even and and you know uh
move towards 4 e cognition but um at the
same times I I had a very hard time to
actually apply this to my work done in
cognitive Neuroscience because after my
master uh program I did a PhD in medical
physics at the Medical University I was
working together with physicist we uh
mostly focused in uh um neuroimaging but
also uh Dynamic caal modeling then and
uh but they didn't really care for these
ideas from cognitive science I mean
those 4E models that we tried to come up
with back then quite honestly they were
very uh uh useless for cogn
neurs and um so they always knew okay
I'm the guy who knows how to code and
because of my computer science
background I also worked in the industry
they knew that they could give me some
data and then I will make sense of it
and this is how how how they basically
um yeah um handled me uh but they knew
that I had this kind of esoteric side
coming from cognitive science you know
always questioning the paradigms and and
and um not thinking that the brain is
just reactive right then at one point I
came up with um with uh my interest in
in predictive processing and finally I
mean the big confirmation was when when
people uh like Carl and Andy Clark also
started talking about it then people uh
realized oh okay it's not only Ronnie
saying something like this about
productive processing it's also other
people and this is how it got a little
bit more accepted but honestly there
were this basically two camps in in
Vienna one very much into this kind of
neobehaviorism and the other one more
for E inspired in cognitive science and
I was caught in the middle and now I I
try to you know bring those camps
together interesting okay that's cool
yeah so that must have been what sort of
2013 2014 when the you know Andy
clarks's book came out and whatever next
was published and I guess that's when
all the buzz around predictive
processing emerged that's that's
interesting you know it's I love talking
about the actual ideas but I'm also
fascinated in the kind of meta aspect of
people fighting over their ideas um so
so yeah so we had sort of fory and then
then very strict computational accounts
and then act of
inference just sticking with for and act
of inference because I feel like those
are the two that are kind of
spearheading cognitive science at the
moment do you sense that they're
compatible um there's been a there's
been a real tension I would say between
sort of the traditional an activist
cognition side and autopoetic side and
more let's say representation forms of
active inference where do you kind of
see the middle ground there and and
their
Confluence yeah I think they're totally
compatible I because I mean like I said
I'm I'm coming from uh autois and and
this was was was the big the big
motivation actually to seek out a kind
of model that
somehow um yeah accommodates uh the the
ideas of autop prasis and so it was only
natural for me um to stumble on the free
energy principle at some point and say
yeah this is this is how I think we can
interface those those ideas to basically
have something tangible to have
something that can make experimental
predictions um in terms of you know how
you interpret behavioral data but also
neuroimaging data and so on but the same
time in its foundation is already also
integrated in the ideas of uh autop
poesis and um you self-regulation so
this was already f for me from the start
and now what I learn is that there are
some semantic differences um I would say
where people say no no no this is not
the kind of an activism and body
cognition that we uh want to have and um
yeah I mean for me those differences are
not so severe I would say I I would like
to leave this uh debate to philosophers
where you say okay this is maybe it's
just my too sloppy reading of of the
material but um in his foundation I
think it's totally compatible and I
think if we work together I and get the
semantics right and and what we actually
want to achieve I think we can come up
with a very nice unified model to uh
bring the whole cognitive science
together fantastic I love the optimism I
share it uh because I I also love the
earlier work of verella and rash and
Thompson and then you know vel's later
work in the 90s actually trying to
bridge the phenomenology with the
neurology and the neuroscience and I
think all of that stuff is fascinating
uh orbe it incomplete that that as you
say like we're still working towards
those generative passages but um
excellent and and it's funny that you
did physics as well right because then
you fold in the kind of so-called high
road to active inference
and the basian mechanics and the [ __ ]
plank equation and the
longans was it cool to see all of that
come into the picture given your
mathematical
background so I have to say I'm not a
real physicist I worked with physicists
so which means that all the ideas that I
had I always discussed in the in our
coffee room and they always feedback on
it so it had to make sense in the
physical world but this doesn't
necessarily mean that I understand what
the [ __ ] plank equation is really
about right so um yeah I have to admit
um this is not my my uh my biggest uh
expertise in the the field fair enough
fair enough me neither so let's not even
go there um I wanted to ask again before
jumping onto the amigdala um I thought
this realtime fmri idea is
fascinating um and I was really I guess
it's not it doesn't need to be too
related to active inference I guess the
nice thing about this podcast is we can
just as I said before we went on go
wherever um how does that work and why
was real time fmri a historical
challenge was it just people just didn't
think about it or did it prove uh
challenging to
um
predecessors so I mean first of all it
takes quite some uh some time to to
process the FM data so um uh I I think
it goes back to like 2006 where where
the first people started to do real time
fmri um and back then there were many
pragmatic challenges back then so how to
get the images quickly off the scanner
onto some computer to do the
analysis and um these things have um you
have been res solved over the next
couple of years so the scanner
manufacturers were more accommodating to
the researchers needs and this was this
really improved the field and then also
uh data analysis and
pre-processing um was was was very much
improved by new methods to do that
really in real time I mean one
fundamental problem that still exists is
that there is this hemodynamic DeLay So
you always when you do functional MRI um
you don't measure neural activity
directly you measure the blood flow in
the brain which means there's always a
delay by um about six seconds uh when
you have the peak uh of the hemic
response and some people said for
philosophical reasons that this is much
too late actually for somebody to
interfere so if you want to you know
regulate your own brain then you will
always see the uh the um the e um the
outcome of this regulation effort about
6 seconds uh later and so some people
say okay I mean this means by principle
real time FM is impossible for for neuro
feedback but um I disagree I think the
um humans are very good in association
learning I mean they can uh um they can
steer huge trucks you know trucks much
larger than they are they can huge
carrier ships whatsoever so um this is
what you can basically learn by getting
used uh to the uh to the task and um and
and yeah getting getting a little bit of
training and when I wanted to do when I
was when I was studing my PhD uh uh
program actually so I had a job
interview by my supervisor Kristen
wesburger real hardcore fmri physicist
uh from from the early days of FM
actually and he asked me okay so Ronnie
what would you like to do after all so
what what is your career goal and said
oh I really would like to learn this
real time from Ry and back then he said
no way this is not going to work no
there's so many technical challenges and
um first you should really learn your
proper FM and also a little bit Dynamic
Cal modeling uh which was quite on walk
back uh back then it came up as a new uh
method and this was absolutely the right
choice so I didn't waste any time uh
during my PhD to you know uh you know
spend endless uh uh time in the lab to
really set up the those those pipelines
so I waited a couple of years for my
first uh uh post abroad um in in surich
at the bule Clinic um where I had the
opportunity to work with Fran chowski
was also at UCL um at the welcome trust
Center where he also was one of the
pioneers of of real time fmr and this is
where we started and this is how we um
got it going and we set up um a small uh
pilot uh experiment I would call it so
with different interventions people had
to regulate their own Amala so I'm I'm
always a little bit
Centric uh we instruct the people inside
the scanner to either up or down
regulate Thea and we used uh emotional
faces as feedback so one instruction was
for example to make um neutral faces
happy so we used morph faces and then
they looked more and more happy and uh
or to downregulate the amula by making
uh fearful faces less fearful m
cool and so so it's you know people it's
difficult you know as you know as an
experimentalist it's hard sometimes to
understand exactly what your
participants are doing in a brain scan
or when they're doing an experiment I
presume you was asking them question as
as quality to like what tactic are you
using because you've got this sixc delay
but then you've also got this functional
like oh you've got like let's see how
you're actually actively um modulating
the response of your amigdala what kind
of reasons did people come up with even
if they're kind of spurious and and post
hog yeah uh I mean we uh we didn't have
a systematic way of asking those
questions but I wanted to um do some qu
qualitative analysis of of the data and
you know just to collect some samples of
what people are reporting what kind of
strategies they might be using or not
and so I always asked them how certain
they were that they were performing well
and um so this
was yeah not not really indicative of
their actual performance so I I remember
this one particular participant she was
absolutely stunning she was really able
to up or down regulate Thea at will you
could really see how the signals would
go up would go down again so it really
like this textbook example what you show
in a post is a typical subject and then
we asked her so how satisfied were you
with your regulation and she said oh no
it could have been better and I'm not
sure and um when you also ask him for
strategies what kind of um strategies
they used it was also very hard to
pinpoint because some people had really
uh good ideas so some people had
experience with meditation some um some
were maybe a little bit from a
psychology background and had some
training uh in in Psychotherapy and they
did let's say um um different cognitive
regulation mechanisms that a priori
would make lots of sense but they failed
on the other hand we had some some guys
from um let's say from the eth so from
Technical University there and uh they
said yeah without knowing anything about
the brain actually said yeah I was just
lying there and thinking about playing
basketball with this person I'm seeing
and reason
so so the only the only thing that um
that seemed to work was to consistently
pay attention to uh what you're doing so
if you're trying too hard if you you
know try to adapt a very complex
regulation strategy or something um and
you don't manage to focus your attention
for the whole time then it will not work
but if you're very consistent with your
strategy I think that brain can also
take care of the rest maybe oh this is
okay this is really cool this is really
interesting I'd love to go a little bit
further into this um so just so I can
get some sort of clarity on the Paradigm
um you're showing people these faces
some of which are you're expecting to
raise igdal activity and others you're
expecting to sort of downregulate igd
activity and so where does the
self-regulation aspect come in and um
they're not party to the actual the fmr
information of their amigdala is that
right um it is so is basically so they
can see what's they can kind of see what
going on and so why would so my question
there is why would that person not think
they're doing very well if they can see
that they sort of conscious well again
philosophically Sticky words here but
like their will their activity their
attention is actually having this
modulatory effect so why would they have
this like uh this kind of
self-deprecating self
reflexivity yeah it it might be hard to
really quantify how uh and um to really
know how good good you are in in
relationship to to um um to other people
baby maybe because um uh yeah they don't
they don't have much experience with
that and they might be a little
dissatisfied if it takes longer than
expected if you know they try to focus
but they also see the signal going in
the other direction for a brief moment
this so it's very hard to tell actually
okay so people just have very high
standards um so so okay so let's let's
just get some clarity on the Paradigm so
we've got these faces different faces
the so that's going to kind of um
exogenously affect the amigdala but then
you've got you've been telling these
participants okay we want to see if you
can contribute to that process so let's
say I'm looking at a happy face um what
would you be saying to the participant
in that sort of context and what effects
would you be hypothesizing that you
might
see so what we know from the literature
is that mucular activity scales with the
intensity of the emotions that someone
is is perceiving and um so what you see
is there is already some kind of uh um
uh dependency of the stimulus that is
shown and what how the aric should
response so in a way what we talk about
here is a closed loop between um between
the stimulus uh that is also uh um uh
depending on the activity and uh you as
the agent inside the MRI scanner are
somehow in the position to manipulate in
that so find a way to to influence this
closed loop between what the amula is
doing in processing the faces and what
is actually
presented and uh I mean this was without
much Theory actually so there are are
control theoretical assumptions on that
that you're somehow regulating uh this
uh disclosed Loop but um at some at some
point we could also come up with an
active inference mod lecture what might
be going on there right yeah yeah it
definitely lends itself to a kind of
hierarchical modeling perspective where
you have kind of higher order
constraints I guess it was the uh was
the role of the kind of endogenous
attention or endogenous will to always
like oppose the closed loop so if for
example I'm seeing a very fearful face
so we're expecting this to correlate
with increased the migler activity would
it always would the task always be well
try and deregulate or or down regulate
the activity of and maybe if it was
again I'm just asking I wasn't there uh
but if uh if there sort of minimal
activity because you're just see a very
neutral face you might say well try and
try and Spike it was it always kind of
doing the inverse of what might be
happening
endogenously no we actually did several
interventions with that what we found
what was working best was actually to
either downregulate the to make fearful
faces less fearful and um neutral faces
more happy by upregulating DEA so if it
was um somehow consistent with uh with
this natural
tendencies um then uh then it it work
best I would say wow this is I really
like this this is cool so um as you say
it kind of lends itself to this active
inference hierarchical perspective
I believe you did I know this is a weird
thing but obviously I search up everyone
I'm speaking to just so I can do my
intro and stuff and I think I saw that
you did some work on
shophow um I it was a long time ago it
was your Master's work right that's
right yeah shop shophow does you know
shophow focuses very much on the
will what I mean this question just came
to me so it sounds very contrived and
but it really isn't um what role would
you say this points you know for a kind
of naive audience or folk psychology
audience it might say well of course
this is just the will this is me doing
it this is like purposeful activity and
I can control my thoughts and I can
control my actions and so on what what
do you see being the kind of uh
operating um function or operating
mechanism in play here in terms of top
down
regulation yeah that's interesting I
mean
um so when it comes to the brain now um
I would say it has something to do with
prefrontal control of
thexa uh if we talk about yeah more um
metaphysical accounts What Chow could
give with with metaphysical will I mean
a short explanation first because this
is yeah as you said this was my master
thesis and I stumbled in schopenhauer
while um reading a little bit of uh
philosophical literature in my third and
fourth semester in my Congress science
studies so wienstein but also
schopenhauer then I was really
fascinated by how many interesting ideas
he already had in the um 19th century
and I thought that many of the things
that he was talking about are still
state-of-the-art discussions in
cognitive science and that's why I I
tried to you know apply some of his
ideas to um to current problems that we
have that's why I called my master
thesis schopenhauer's last will
and um it's not very good
philosophically speaking because I'm not
a trained philosopher but it was um it
was very interesting actually to uh to
step into this debate and discuss with
philosophers about it and this was was
really informative but this was kind of
a a singular point in my uh history
before I moved on again to the more
empirical more uh uh cognitive
Neuroscience side of cognitive science
but let's talk about the will now and
the way I interpret shophow so I mean at
one point I really want to take a
philosopher and write a proper paper
about it but I think chenhow had lots of
interesting things to say um that are
still relevant for active infrance as
well because he talked about two things
about representations and will the world
is Will and representation and
representations
um have a lot to do with the models that
we are using uh in in cognitive science
so he didn't use of course
representation this loaded fashion that
um that we now have in cogntive science
where the representation Wars um but uh
it was the the the the the German word
of representation would be forell which
is like an imagination so there is some
kind of um uh imagination going on that
I used to actually uh model the world so
we cannot access uh access the world
directly so he was very much influenced
by c um there's only the only the
consequences the phenomena are somehow
uh reachable to us and based on that we
form imaginations representations of the
world and for him of course this was not
enough and I mean when we now translate
it also to predictive process and we see
okay just you know s yeah collecting
samples of the world and compiling it
somehow this would be very passive uh
predictive coding without any intention
without life it is just a way of of
storing data and so so shopen how
already needed to have this kind of
second uh uh Power at work and this
would be the will and the will was
nothing um meta um metaphysically rich
in the sense that there was some uh God
and its will and uh it has some some
yeah it was more a force of nature very
much undirected so he would say on the
most primitive level um it's it's the
laws of nature
uh that are a manifestation of this will
and then when you go up uh on uh on
living in in the Hur of living systems
he had this very strong hierarchical
view you see that plants somehow manage
to fight against gravity because they're
growing upwards and and you you get from
there to animals and then uh human
beings but in essence they are a
manifestation of the same will of the
same um force of life or maybe of the
same principles that we have in nature
when we think of thermodynamics for
example we need to find a way to fight
the second law of Thermodynamics right
and these mechanisms um could uh could
be yeah could link to this merry
metaphorical idea of will interesting
cool yeah yeah yeah I mean obviously
yeah the notion of a
will especially of a sixc
delay is uh is tricky right um
philosophically but I think it's it's
not a it's not a it's not an it's not a
redundant question some philos you know
the really strict materialists might
just say well it is just the prefrontal
cortex uh but at least on this podcast I
don't hold any ontological requirements
so if you wanted to say that it's a pan
psychist Proto agent or if you wanted to
say it's God I'm I'm I'm I'm gonna
entertain it but at least in terms of
what I would like to say to be a little
bit more precise about my idea of of
free will is not necessarily you know
philosophers somehow like to uh detach
the actual problem of living systems to
very abstract spaces where time doesn't
play a role and for me six seconds delay
are um is not
really a problem because I think uh that
uh agency has no nothing to do with uh
you know moment to on the level of
moment to moment but also in the level
of process that you are causing
something you you see the outcome of
your actions you might not be even aware
of uh um of of the behavior that uh gave
rise to these outcomes but then you
evaluate the outcomes and then you learn
from it and then you adjust your
behavior I think uh in in this kind of
ballp part this is where most of free
will actually happens because most of
the behavior that we do is automatic and
and for good reasons because it's
efficient and fast but over your
continuous uh effort you're able to uh
steer um
yourself also when you have very delay
feedback like in Neo
feedback yes yes I think I think a lot
of these sort of broader
philosophical questions are underpinned
by your like resting Axiom if you're
taking the notion of a substantial self
a cartisian dualistic self then sure
like it it the time probably doesn't
matter right there might just be a delay
but if you're just taking this neurophys
phological
mechanisms well then we're not going to
get off the ground by even talking about
you recognizing the consequences of your
own action I think it's funny because
shophow also said I believe uh a man can
do what he Wills but he can't will what
he Wills which I just a beautiful
reputation to kind of soft determinism I
always thought was the best reputation
of soft determinism which is like yeah
yeah yeah like I'm doing what I want but
I'm like well why did you choose this
that you know why did you choose what
you wanted and you run that infinite
regret
he he was a brilliant writer he was
really really great in um you know
making really good points really uh um
uh really uh high in rhetorics and
everything uh but the point was I I
think that he was misguided and in a
couple of ways and I I think it has
something to do with his lifestyle he
was he was a very odd person he was
living alone he didn't have um much
social interactions and uh also he was
very mean to friends and people
interested in him so um yeah never a
family never a relationship whatsoever
so I think he has had a um very
depressive uh deposition and um and I
think so I mean this is what now now we
move back into into into the clinical
Neuroscience domain maybe when we look
at people uh with uh depressive symptoms
they also tend uh uh to be more um
uh
incompatibilism uh basically driven by
external factors right so there could be
this interesting relationship there as
well oh yeah yeah go ahead go ahead
please and so because I mean it was kind
of a dead end for him life it was always
uh was it was always governed by
external factors and there was no way
out and um this it just drove him to
this extremely strong nihilism and also
his uh idea of anti-natalism actually
it's better to um not have any you know
offsprings at all and to die out at one
point so it's very dark very um uh um
nihilistic and this is definitely the
side that I don't like about it yeah
also here disregard for
women yeah well they were all pretty
rubbish in that domain I think you know
um yeah I think we can kind of we can in
some sense those elements of those
philosophers um the disparaging
attitudes towards women just kind of
that element Dooms them all uh I'm not
sure shophow is an exemption that I mean
of course there are some who were a bit
nicer but I think they were all pretty
twatty in that domain so that's not
great um that's really interesting yeah
you you hear this stuff about sort of
locust of control internal versus
external locus of control and it
correlates with um meaning and lies and
and depression and stuff like that I
think what's interesting there is even
to make that point just on a
philosophical basis you're you you're
still you're still investing in this
kind of physicalist Axiom which I just
don't think is particularly well
substantiated by science or by
philosophy or by whatever it you know
this notion that well we we just don't
know um because we have this
remarkable ability to be subjectively
aware of things and have intentional
stuff answers on things and well Ronnie
if you can find a person who can explain
that to me then you win right and I'll
become shophow and nihilistic but until
then I'm quite happy to sort of bathe in
the the loveliness of that mystery and I
wonder whether if shophow had read
Thomas Nagel or David Charmers whether
he would have been a bit more optimistic
but you know I think you sense a lot of
this in this the scientific turn in the
19th century uh yeah and the 20th
century this this gross nihilism which
obviously n basically foretold more than
anyone so this is I mean so I think this
your your integration here of the
therapeutic landscape is interesting as
well because you know this is very broad
brush and rough but a lot of therapy
especially for something like an anxiety
disorder will be will look something
like reestablishing the prefrontal
cortex as the master over the
amigdala so I'm worried that the world
is going to fall down or plane is going
to crash or well like you know this why
people like Vagas nerve breathing but
let's reestablish the role of the
prefrontal cortex to moderate and
regulate uh that
overactivity but it almost sounds like
okay if we focus so much on that
neuroanatomy we almost lead into an
nihilism because well the prefrontal
cortex isn't me right if you showed me
my little flesh of prefrontal Cortex I
wouldn't say oh well that's my will
that's my desire that's my capacity for
regulation so what was your experience
when you saw that people were able to
regulate their amydala regulate their
emotions was it liberating for them or
were they kind of spooked
out so yeah that's that's an interesting
point um so yeah because this is
actually where where I'm also coming
from I always thought of the being
regulated by the prefrontal cortex so uh
uh this was also my main focus in my PhD
thesis worked with people with social
anxiety disorders and um you could see
in neurotypical people that uh when they
were watching emotional faces they were
able to down regulate the amula um by uh
by by a small region called the medial
orbital frontal cortex and precisely
this mechanism was not functioning so
well in people with social anxieties
order and in another study where people
were uh given uh ssris so anti % uh
medication uh they were able to have
stronger down regulation of the amular
or with the frontal cortex so this very
much played into uh uh into this kind of
narrative and this is also what we find
in the neuro feedback study that uh
people who regulate the Amala also have
stronger influence of the am of the
prefrontal cortex on the Amala so this
kind of of works it it it um it has
something uh also to do with with the uh
studies on um uh cognitive uh effort and
how people are doing cognitive
reappraisal and then are able to uh
regulate subcortical areas by using
prefrontal areas so this kind of network
but you're right this is not the full
story yes well we can't we yeah we'll
move on but I guess I'm I'm really just
trying to Ram home we can't discard the
phenomenology uh and as a fore man I'm
sure you're you're you agree yeah but
you see where my problem actually is so
uh I I I kind of accepted this kind of
narrative that we use in in clinical
neuroscience and cognitive Neuroscience
to uh Model A mucular connectivity right
and um what I've been actually
struggling with the um uh with the topic
of amuka and active inance was for many
years so like more than 10 years I was
not able to B basically bring those two
together I I that I was a mucular
research uh Searcher during the week and
on the weekend I could think about
active inance but those were things that
were highly compart comp
compartmentalized I couldn't bring them
together uh why because I mean it was
you you could say okay I have to think
about top down control of T MCA but like
you said I was not happy just to say
okay it should have something to do with
the um with the prefrontal cortex and
the prefrontal cortex regulating but
yeah there's more to that you mentioned
um breathing
you basically a link also to uh
inceptive
processes will regulate also deala so if
you are uh if you have a panic attack it
has nothing to do with what you're
thinking you're experiencing that you're
losing control of your body and this
alone is enough it has nothing to do
with some kind of abstract reasoning
that you're doing it is an embodied
process that should play a role so um
then the other thing is uh so it has
something to do with the insular cortex
then maybe or it has something to do
also with uh brain stem inut into the
am um the other thing is then also
reward processing because um much of the
debate is is focused on on uh fear
conditioning experiments in animals
because it works so nicely uh and this
is where you say okay this is um this is
the function of the amula it's about
fear and threat processing or something
and even in my um in my PhD thesis I
wrote about also the U you know that
nuclear all responds to positive
emotions and I had a big fight with one
of the uh reviews of my PhD thesis
because I said no the is just for fear
even though it already outdated this
kind of few back then but yeah nowadays
we know so much more from animal
experiments that um the amula is is
heavily connected with the vent stum so
it has a lot to do with you know uh
making the decisions about risk and
rewards and balancing those and um so we
now know from the animal models very
precise mapping so those those circuits
definitely exist somehow
and so this is another eonr then so
where should I start to actually uh draw
the top level of the hierarchy you say
okay this okay the amler is driven by
reward no we could also say that no the
am is driven by interception and uh
therefore I kind of failed to come up
with a way to start my active inurance
model and this shifted then a little bit
later when I had this inside for for the
transy cognitive science paper yeah yeah
we we'll certainly come to the text
paper I guess one thing yeah one
interesting addition to this uh
conversation that the pre the the loop
between the pref CeX and the amigdala is
not enough is OCD and OCD is interesting
because it was cast as an anxiety
disorder and this you know and so you
would say okay well cognitive behavioral
therapy is about reinstating the role of
the prefrontal cortex but OCD actually
involves hyperactivity of the orbital
frontal cortex and so and how that maps
on to therape you know therapeutically
is they'll say don't do loging don't do
rumination don't do don't logic your way
out of um a problem right that's
actually worsening the problem so and
and what's odd is that in many ways the
symptoms of OCD are very similar to the
sympt Syms of something like Gad or
generalized anxiety disorder and yet it
seems like there's the inverse
relationship or the inverse problem
where you have hyperactivity over the
frontal cortex and so you have stuff
like TMS or you know intrusive Lees
going in there and actually trying to
deregulate that process so it's um it's
a mystery but as you say it's it of
course it's a mystery because it's you
know hundreds of millions of years old
it would be lovely if it was just one
Loop uh but alas okay so let's um let's
jump to this tix paper um your Trends in
cognitive science paper on the amigdala
so you called it the amigdala complex
which I really liked uh I thought it was
kind of it sounded kind of Victorian
um before you fold an act of inference
into the amydala you mentioned that you
you know one of your reviewers of your
PhD went well amigdalas are only for
fear what are the other kind of
preconceptions that historically have
held about the amydala I would say that
there is only one amigdala but
essentially what's what's very important
is I mean of course there are two they
are bilateral but um even more important
the lateralization is that the amular
consists of at least two completely
different nuclei and the one would be
the Central
amca and the other one um the
basolateral complex so these are
actually two different um nuclei that
somehow are fused together or um over
time and the origin of the centrala is
actually the the vent
strum and while the uh basal and lateral
part of the amula actually more cortical
Lian
structure so this was this this is an
important game Cher already I mean many
people in the um in the rodent
literature know about this I mean they M
the differences between central lular
medial lulara all the different parts of
the basolateral uh complex
and they're totally familiar with that
but in human Neuro Imaging we mostly
focus on the whole amuka or just some
active voxels within the gross
neighborhood of where Thea might be or
something so it's it's um it's very
unclear when we look at the neuroimaging
uh data what we actually mean when we
talk about Thea because uh many groups
uh talking about different
things and it may be worth just
unpicking for the non TR audience when
you say so the central mdala um well
actually I guess people are coming from
an active inference hierarchy so when I
was reading I was thinking okay the
central migler is higher up the
hierarchy uh and provides predictions to
the basil lateral area but when you say
okay emerges from the vental striatum so
it has something to do with motivation
and reward and the basolateral feeds
back into the sensory cortex if we now
feed in these classic terms of
perception and action which are kind of
the currency of active inference what
does that say more broadly about these
different bits if that's a feasible
distinction okay let's let's start maybe
with um with the different historical
views so let's say um the simple human
neuroimaging view might be the Amala is
something like a fear detector or
Emotion Detector or relevance detector
something something like this and if uh
let's say a a new emotional phis pops up
then the would increase its activity
this is the a traditional few in neurom
imaging and many experiments are done
this way and there yeah some really good
experiments and you can learn a lot um
from this kind of mular re activity the
more nuanced fuse nowadays in
Neuroscience would be to say okay let's
look at the different sub nucle um let's
say in a mouse model for example to say
okay we have the Bas latal Mula at one
end at the lateral end of the Bas
lateral Mula you have unimodal inputs
and those are integrated towards um the
more basal part and become a multimodal
uh um uh in integrated uh stimuli and uh
from there there's an um there's a
connection to the central amula and the
central am would then be the output
region so there's some kind of gating
that is modulated by let's say ventrum
or prefrontal cortex or whatever and um
there basically decisions are made if uh
you should show some kind of
stereotypical uh threat response like
fining Behavior or fighting or running
away so it um very much um depends on
the context what kind of behavior is
actually uh used to get away from this
kind of situation and this is the
mainstream view yeah what I tried to do
is then to to basically flip it around
to say no Central amula is is not uh um
just receiving the uh the signal but it
is actually the one that is on top of
the hierarchy and sending down
predictions to the Bas Metro to that and
do you so yeah that's great so do you
then uh reconfigure or recast this
gating mechanism as a contextualization
mechanism would that be fair would that
be fair to
say I mean so many of the things that we
are seeing in this paper are very
compatible with what people already know
so many people who follow the classical
feed forward perspective would say yeah
of course what uh uh the output of the
central amula is additionally gated by
input from insula PFC ventum and
potentially also other areas and um so
this already um already is there but for
me the big question was actually but how
does the basal amular know what kind of
data to forward to the central amular so
what is Rel for the for the centrala and
this big question of meaning and
relevance this is something that is not
answered in the classical feed forward
uh Paradigm this is what we had to
change so it's worth pointing out there
that the transmission of information
from the unimodal to the multimodal to
something like the abstract level at the
central migdala is not
necessarily it doesn't it doesn't it's
not like a replication process there s
like stripping out of information as it
gets p up the hierarchy is that is that
is that fair in terms of relevance
meaning and yeah I mean personal
relevance right it's it's going to be
individual specific
what do you therefore suggest that those
nonrelevant stul like just get as we say
explained away yeah exactly so it's it's
a kind of abstraction gradiant as I like
to call it so you you get away from very
concrete uh sensory features more to
something uh uh generalized uh that is
maybe even detch charged from the
context is uh uh longer also in time and
and um so in the temporal Dynamics
actually so you uh um so you explain
smaller stimulus features to fluctuate
more uh uh more quickly than um you know
the object identity for example or the
the effective state that you are in
where you think that you are currently
under threat or uh even that you're in a
a constant state of anxiety for
example yeah so so we can so just for
like yeah just for myself and the
audience it's kind of this idea that we
have these slower contextual
fluctuations which can regulate the
faster fluctuations so maybe maybe an
example would be worth using here so I I
like I really like your example I
actually used it as well and I genuinely
did not take it I just uh it may have
been something that Carl mentioned but
it's the kind of snake on the lawn rope
on the lawn dichotomy so you have a rope
in your lawn
and it's kind of curled up in the grass
so you don't know whether it's a snake
or not now your lower level parts of the
amydala are just responding to the
sensory input which
is snake like right the curled the
texture but then you have this higher
order contextual prior that no you're in
your garden right so you're in Australia
I'm in London like we we don't have
snakes what where do you find that um to
meet and therefore the prediction error
uh gets suppressed is that in the
central mdore or is that higher
up so I would say that um the central
amula has more uh something to do with
uh having a general feeling of how safe
you are at the moment safe also in terms
of how well you are regulated and how
well you expect to be regulated in the
future so if you experience experiencing
pain or death in the near future then
you're not saved and this is something
you should be afraid of and this is
where I think the centrala plays a role
so if there
is sufficient contextual evidence that
uh okay you are in a tropical jungle and
there might be snakes out there um then
you're of course more on the edge so and
this would mean that you're upregulating
uh uh those parts of the amula the basal
Milla that is very good in detecting
those uh those snakes while when you are
in a safe context when you are sailing
this is the ex example that I'm I'm I'm
using in the paper not you know that
there many ropes lying around but there
usually no snakes um then uh you should
be actually quite at EAS and not
misinterpret all coiled uh snake like
objects as snakes yeah I think I think
this is really I think this is really
interesting I think it's an area that
actually I've been talking to some
people about this the fact that I don't
think these attentional mechanisms are
actually that well articulated in Act of
inference literature there are some
wonderful papers I keep pointing people
in the p uh direction of miter and his
papers on attention with Carl and others
but I think this is a really interesting
point because I view attention in some
way as a uh as a mental action which
involves priors and so for me I when I
talk about the prior in terms of
attention for me it's like okay we we
recognize through these uh slower
contextual cues where you are and that
constitutes um sort of as you say there
prior involved here in the down
regulation of gain control or the down
weighting and precision waiting over
anything which might fit the template of
a
snake but then people I guess generally
think of that in terms of the likelihood
distribution right so what are the you
know given my state what's the the
likelihood of having this observation of
a snake but for us we're kind of saying
well actually this might be constrained
by higher order uh action
policy maybe it's worth unpicking
because I think one reason I really
really liked your paper and I think it's
a really fascinating paper is because I
think more than anyone I've actually
ever read you unpicked the problem with
the ambiguity of the term
prior so you say there are two types of
priors there's kind of the phenotypic
prior or what you call the preferred
prior I believe preference prior
preference prior very good and then you
talk about the prior's aiding perception
so kind of the the priors I've been
talking about here in terms of um
suppressing prediction error um and then
also belief updating so maybe it's worth
putting on your teaching hat and just
saying okay we can keep using the snake
example for people who are very confused
at this point because they're like why
are we using the word prior for these
things maybe it's worth you on helping
us sort of unpick those two senses of
the word prior MH okay so yeah I'm I'm
sometimes very liberal with using the
word prian you know this comes actually
from this cognitive science debate of
whether you have a model or you are a
model and I think it's it's usually both
so metaphorically we can say that our
body and yeah the fact that our Body
Works in this kind of environment that
it is a very good model on on its
environment and I think the same also
applies for PRI I think you are able to
um construct uh prior that you're able
to um to uh
introspectively assess and also report
and do reasoning about it but I think
that some priers are just let's say
hardwired in a way I sometimes do U use
this as an example uh for my students I
would say that even the the bone
structure the skull these are also prior
in a way they're very inflexible highly
precise prior but in a way they allow us
the whole organism to do inference about
the world right and then maybe C
differentiating that from uh the second
type where you say that these priors and
here I can quote Aid perception by
guiding attention enhancing the relevant
signal features and suppressing noise in
Sensations how so that's one side the
homeostatic prize the preference prize
these are somewhat fixed unless you're
sleeping and you can let your body
temperature go down but that as side
they're somewhat
fixed how what's the difference between
those and these priors involved in
perceptual belief
updating right I mean I I always like to
make this distinction um between uh
predictive coding and um predictive
processing or active inference so maybe
some of my students are watching now and
this is a typical example question I
like to give for the mass defend you I'm
so jealous of these these kids kids as
well am I talking about but I'm so
jealous great exam question so I mean
difference is now perceptual prior can
be seen in this uh very stupid uh
operative coding way so you have just a
system that just tries to absorb uh the
environment as it is to minimize uh the
the the difference between what is
actually sensed and what it already
knows so this is coding nothing really
interesting so to speak from from the uh
from from from from cognitive science or
from this idea of organizing a living
system I think the interesting point
comes if you say no it's not only about
updating uh uh your ban beliefs it's
also about uh ban regulation and this is
another formalism basically that you can
easily introduce uh into the whole idea
of uh of Bion processing by saying no
some of the priers they don't update
they are fixed so in terms of perception
this is to give you a very simple
example you might have the idea that
there could be a snake out somewhere you
take a look around and you don't see any
snake so you update your prior belief
okay well I heard something but there is
no snake so this is okay so it's easy to
update those very flexible
priors um but there are some priors that
have to be are more or less fixed and
that's for example ideal uh body
temperature or blood oxygenation for
example right sometimes I hear as a
criticism of people who are not familiar
with predictive processing to say oh
wait why don't you just update your
prediction that you you'll die of course
you die and this has something to do
with uh um fixed preferences that you
have and so there is no way of actually
reducing prediction error and I think
having prediction error on on on on some
levels of of your uh of your hierarchy
and this is something that we have to
learn uh and figure out experimentally
in the future where it actually where it
actually plays the biggest role uh leads
to the feeling of uh negative veilance
so if there is prediction error that you
cannot minimize it doesn't feel right
there is something something very wrong
about it so the only thing and this now
closes the loop how you can actually uh
minimize the prediction error between
your Sensations that you're having for
example to little oxygen and your
homeostatic set points your preference p
is by doing actions you can you know uh
breathe again you can if you're too cold
you can put on a jacket so um this is
how action is the only way of actually
making this right again yeah yeah and as
I've said to my audience or many times
this is perfectly cast within the
variation of free energy
um equation itself right reducing K
Divergence recognition density in the
true posterior then also maximizing
model evidence I guess so two things
come to my mind here the first is that
we also talk about now we're using these
pomdp schemes and Baye graphs we also
talk about priors over um States or or
or and priors over paths and prior over
action so we're talking about you know
preferences sensory prefer sensory
observations of my action or we're
talking about State Transitions and
we're talking about e you know the eent
so we're talking about habits so I guess
the reason why I bring that up is
because for me it's an incomplete
picture without mentioning that because
in many
ways right I might for me I actually
think it's important to divorce these
different types of priors because
without that I might say well I have an
inflexible if I if I say that they're
all one type I have this inflexible
prior that I don't want to be around
snakes but that means I get this
perceptual information right with
precise uh likelihood distribution that
I'm probably you know this observation
is quite likely given that there's a
snake but I don't uh update that prior
so I'm in real trouble right because
there's a snake but I'm not updating it
but I guess the point here is well if I
recognize at the higher level of the
hierarchy that I am in a jungle for
example I can now start doing this
mental action where I through my mental
action increase gain control over the
likelihood distribution the a matrix and
downregulate my uh prior right that
doesn't mean that I discard my
homeostatic requirements it just means
it's more likely that there's going to
be a snake and I'm going to respond
accordingly um I think a really useful
piece of terminology here actually comes
from Sam J nagoshi who who works with
verses and is writing this textbook on
basium mechanics because he talks about
uh perceptual priors and what he calls
autonomous priors and these autonom
priors are these like genetically
determined or or or very you know deep
rooted learn cultural priors which as
you say are super high precision and um
not affected by the idiosyncratic
context in which we find ourselves so
maybe it's it's it's worth picking up
here the role of
attention uh I'm talking about the sort
of hierarchy here the picture that I've
laid out does that does that sound okay
and does it kind of conflate issues by
adding in like a third type of Prior
which are the prior over action no I
don't think so I I think it totally
makes sense um so I mean the am uh
cannot solve all the problems on its own
so it has to be somehow integrated in
that I mean this is this is what we uh
how we also tried to reframe this whole
idea of um uh of seeing the central
amular is the only output region I think
that every part of the amula has its
output um that player relevance here in
this kind of uh um uh uh perceptual and
action hierarchy so the thing is when
you um when you when you talk about
attention I think that uh predictions
from uh the uh lateral am to the
unimodal cortices for example um they
upregulate uh uh areas there to be more
sensitive towards incoming stimuli so
this is also a kind of um neural gain
control has something to do with uh
attentional processes uh this uh the
same also for the central Amal it's not
only for for actions but also uh
regulating uh arousal through uh through
the whole body so if it's uppr
regulating arousal um then uh your whole
uh physiology changes your vision the
way you sample the world totally changes
is a top down phenomenon your um um your
way of how you um yeah integrate
interceptive feelings in your body as
well so uh I think there is not just one
attention mechanism I think attention is
also very multi-level process and it's
not only the kind of attention that we
like to think of as um conscious mental
action that we also can do on this kind
of uh agent uh personal level but I
think there are many
uh subpersonal uh uh aspects also
playing a big role in how attention then
uh forms the kind of attentional
experience that we have yeah yeah
precisely precisely EXA exactly um yeah
attent I've been trying to stress in my
own internal dialogue and also with
other people that I see Precision
Precision waiting and attention is three
different things they are not the same
thing right Precision is a very
technical mathematical IAL inverse
entropy Precision waiting is in part
informed by Precision but also context
then and then attention is this kind of
optimization of that Precision waiting
over one tensor so I think that's kind
of useful uh for people
because most people are just used to
hearing well attention is precision
waiting it's like that won't do um I
guess it even like confound this problem
even more you have you start having
stuff like priors over prior so you have
like okay I have a prior about the
actual distribution of my prior but I
think the way that sanre explained this
to me which is really useful is look at
the brain and look how many ridges there
are in the brain right like once you
start actually folding in these
hierarchies it all kind of makes sense
um why the brain looks like that so and
this is an interesting question I guess
because of your expertise in in
neuroscience and neuroanatomy do you
think so we've now brought like four
different priors into the game do you
think that these are going to
look the same uh and I know that's a
very broad brush question but what I
mean when I say look the same is are
they going to have the same signature of
neuronal firing are they going to be is
the is the neurotransmitter associated
with them going to be the same or are we
just giving a semantic blanket to
simplify the situation for something
which is going they're going to be
wildly
different uh that's that's a very good
point I mean the model that we are
proposing this is a kind of functional
model that we're seeing we we we are not
yet sure uh how it will be uh
implemented on a neural level but what
we can say is
um I mean a lot uh uh a lot of the
things moving forward will will have
something to do with uh dopaminergic
Innovation for example but also uh other
neuromodulators I think neuromodulators
will play a big role in uh understanding
uh this Precision model leting but not
only for inference but also for for
learning so um um I very much uh like
Chris matis uh idea of precision
weighted belief updating uh this is a
context that he uh is a concept that he
uses very frequently in in his research
and um so one prediction would be if um
you have no way of uh modulating uh top
down uh Precision
then toic issues keep going then you're
also not updating your your prior
beliefs right if it's if it's just a
very fixed uh uh belief then no way of
modulating it by dopamine for example
you're stuck and this is something that
uh actually uh might take place in uh in
the Centro medial Mula where you have uh
less flexibility uh there's less
Innovation by dopaminergic regions and
this is something that uh is uh yeah is
is now uh
uh yeah basically also of interest for
uh for the effects of serotonergic uh
medication that or even psychedelics
that uh um neuroplasticity might be uh
actually uh increased by by giving large
doses of of Serotonin and this would
then allow for re-update U updating uh
those those preference priers in in
those
areas yeah yes okay in that picture it
sounds like the pre preference priors or
homeostatic prior you're want to call
them are higher up than in some ways the
perceptual priors yeah um okay that's
really interesting because as I said
before to have this flexible updating of
your prior in terms of the perceptual
belief updating you have to downregulate
your Precision waiting over that PRI
that perceptual prior right in turn uh
increase the Precision over the
likelihood distribution of the sensation
but that seems to me to be governed at
the higher level by an action policy
right like do I want to relinquish
Precision over this prior and maybe in
many ways you know we have this idea of
Rebus um which is Carl and robing Carl
Harris's notion that psychedelics
flatten out the PRI landscape but that's
it's a very very neat narrative but
which priors right like all of them at
which level and I think what uh what I'm
really excited about in being an active
inference in the community is this
notion of deep parametric modeling the
idea that we can't just take one slice
of the hierarchy and say that that's
sufficient to account for perception or
action right because it it it runs deep
unfortunately um I wonder yeah I wonder
to kind of go to your
teaching when you say okay this is a
hierarchy and whatever you think is
going on at like the perceptual level is
going to be informed by by the
conceptual level which is going to and
God knows what's at the top how many
this is a very stupid question but how
many layers do you kind of envisage
mentally when you're talking about that
how and and if you can even say where
does it stop what's the kind of guiding
principle so it's definitely
7.2 I've heard people you I've heard
I've heard people say seven I'm not even
joking I've heard people say seven
really
yeah yeah seven or eight or maybe
12 no I mean I now I'm taking on my data
scientist had actually uh if you add uh
layers to a hierarchical model at some
point they will run out of data to
actually process so you will see that
some uh layers will not process anything
so these can gone can be gone and that's
that's what the nervous system is
actually doing so it's it's removing
complexity whenever it can this is Beau
things of the fre principle so if
there's nothing to process they will be
gone and I mean this has a lot in uh
this also nicely links for example to uh
the concept of uh of meditation where
you say okay you basically dis you want
to disengage with your normal way of
being in the world of you know acting on
the world having uh um goals in mind
that you want to achieve but the only
thing that you want to do is just sit
there and be there in this very moment
so what you're actually doing you create
a state where not pro actively
processing anything and you try to you
know just calm everything down that you
see and what is the experience that
you're going to have if you have never
meditated before yeah yeah well yeah
it's just
distraction it's distraction and and the
the the the the effective feeling would
be boredom right right so this is some
way actually you don't have anything to
process at this kind of level you you
feel it une you don't know what to kind
of do with this kind of experience that
you're having but over over long time
when you're trained to that um you will
basically uh yeah get uh maybe uh uh um
also this kind of hierarchical layer
that would be necessary to actually
process this kind of meter meter that's
really nice kind of informative data and
then you get used to it and you're fine
and this is how you can add yet another
uh level of the hierarchy oh that's
really lovely yeah that's cool uh it's
kind of like we're inventing our or or
creating our own Markoff blankets our
intermediate markof blankets between
just I mean which we have right already
I mean of course we do we're deeply
hierarchical beings but I like the idea
that we're kind of we're con it's
context contingent in the sense I you
know I think you mentioned actually in
your paper that the central amigdala was
kind of generally seen as responding to
these kind of
hardwired appetitive or aversive stimuli
right so a tiger or a mango but actually
that hasn't been fleshed out at all in
experimental contexts because stimulus
stimuli have subjective values right
it's we don't all sit down and agree
with God that we want mangoes and we
don't want Tigers because maybe you have
a pet tiger and maybe you're allergic to
mangoes so maybe it's worth I don't know
if you've got anything to say on that
but like as you say there are clearly
some hardw ones that we need to be human
right to be this thing that persists
through time that minimizes variational
free energy but there are also others
which are Downstream on subjective
evaluation where do you kind of do you
see those as two distinct categories
with a bright line between them or do
you see maybe the subjective evaluative
ones emerging from the homeostatic ones
where where's the what's the kind of
interplay between those
two yeah always um when whenever I start
to think about these things it always
looks a little bit like a a gradient uh
so there there I think there are no
exact
boundaries point but I mean some of the
very fixed beliefs we have about how the
world should be I mean they feel very
much real they feel like uh we're losing
parts of ourself of ourselves if we give
up this um I don't know this fact that
we uh seem to believe about the world so
we feel that everything falls down if we
have to give it up even even though it's
just something constructed even so even
if it's just something made up right so
um in a sense you could say that certain
uh um beliefs uh uh have had adaptive
value where you say this might might be
also cultural norms that were uh
transmitted and and so um there might be
some some Merit to it
um but uh um I think it's
uh this uh there's there there still
this gradient of things that you can
easily unlearn and uh and and easily
update and others where you uh we
holding on a little bit
harder yeah yeah yeah yeah cool so now
we've been talking about hierarchies and
the complexity of the human system and
its capacity to adapt you also mentioned
in brief in your paper the the
possibility of engrs in the amydala so
people associate engrs I mean you'll do
a better job at explaining engrams than
I will but with the hippocampus and with
memory um and the way that I read that
in the computational sense is kind of
almost automated behavior um and habits
and really you know strong priors over
uh action so maybe it's worth starting
there with the
neuroanatomy because the amigdala is
connected that has a route to the
hippocampus and then say exactly what
you mean because it sounds like oh the
Amiga has a memory in some sense what
does that mean and what does that how
does that add to this already uh
complicated
story yeah what I like to um stress
because I think this is really important
is that I don't think that there are um
that there are distinct memory and
processing networks in the brain I think
when you look at the and you could say
uh I mean when you use the computer
metaphor it's uh it's both it's both the
CPU and the memory so one neuron already
does this kind of computation and it me
it has memory right so uh sometimes you
know when we when we write uh cognitive
Neuroscience textbooks we like to put
big section headlines and we call one
section uh memory and the other one
decision making for example this is
already what a neuron is doing it has
its thresholds and it has its
memories and the interesting question
now is um what does a memory recognize
actually and um uh some of the features
or some of the neural computational role
neuron is playing is only uh played when
it's actually um when it's spiking when
it shows activity but there is another
aspect a neuron also um can be totally
inactive and already plays a role in
that by for example uh suppressing
inputs that coming in it filters away
noise and this is would be a very energy
efficient way of actually uh doing
neural processing when uh when it just
shuts down things that are not needed
anymore and only propagates those things
that are meaningful deviations and then
news worthy for the other parts of the
hierarchy and this is what I'm actually
mean with uh memory engrams so what what
would that look like in terms of because
for me and I make reference here to this
new paper by George Dean and lar uh SED
Smith and others looking at canalized
Behavior it sounds to me that actually
having kind of engrams or or or kind of
a Proto memory system or a memory system
in the amigdala could be somewhat uh
pathological in the sense that if it's
done you know non if it's a non-adaptive
form of response then we have this
habituated response that we have no
prefrontal cortex regulation over that's
freaking out every time we see um a rope
right because I'm like oh I think that's
a snake or a fa or a face in a rock
because I have social anxiety so what
what what's the Adaptive role of these
kind of uh engrams and yeah what what's
their that being so what's their role
also potentially in something like
psychopathology I mean I kind of see
myself as also following this idea that
uh brought forward by comput uh
competitional Psychiatry people like
Clan and car friston r Dolan uh and also
Phil Colette of course because sometimes
they they like to uh reframe pathologies
in a way to say okay Hey listen people
actually it's coming from a um there's
some kind of good intention behind this
mechanism optim
there's actually an Adaptive value of
depression of anxiety and so on and so
on and in this context I would like to
say yeah I mean it is good to be afraid
of certain things and it's very good to
have this kind of stereotypical uh
reactions those habitual reaction to a
stimulus that is coming if something is
Dashing towards me and I will just you
know raise my arms to protect my face
then this is a very good adaptive
response even though I mean even it
might be a train uh running towards me
and of course my hands will be um quite
futile to useless yeah good luck but I
mean it's the last resort that I have
it's the only thing that I could
potentially do and maybe it helps me but
of course in the modern world it does
not the the thing is uh many of these
things pretty adaptive in in nature uh
but of course something can go wrong um
and the question is uh um is it always
that is it actually going wrong or is it
something that the brain cannot just no
longer adapt to when you think of um of
uh of this preference price many of them
in the Micha I think are acquired during
early parts of your
childhood I mean this is studied in
Mouse models and there is um indirect
evidence also in humans for that so you
basically learn uh what kind of place to
world is whether it's a very dangerous
place or whether it's a safe place and
uh depending on that uh I mean the whole
architecture of of the brain down to the
biochemical level will change so I Mean
Gene regulation is a big thing and uh
the way the DNA is called up around the
histone so How likely it is to for
example uh produce stress hormones uh
the these are things that are already uh
um some some kind of not determined but
influenced already at this early uh uh
Parts in in in in in in development and
developmental Windows where those things
can actually uh uh take place and then
they are there for the rest of your life
in a way if not treated properly if not
unlearned in a way so the thing is they
might have
had an advantage back then you know that
the world is dangerous so you should be
uh fast with your stress responses and
uh so this could be uh then also the
reason for many psychopathologies later
on so some some people then uh will um
find when they are grown up um different
behavioral Solutions so some could be um
yeah they are more anxiety prone because
they know they are always basically the
victim of a situation in a situation but
other people might find that aggression
is actually the goto solution for many
things and um deligent Behavior can be a
consequence from because they basically
avoiding uh being hurt by hurting
somebody else before that but the the
the foundation for that could already be
um basically uh uh um ingrained into
those uh into those preference priors
that are set early during um maturation
yeah that's that's really fascinating
because I think it adds another level of
complexity to this kind of U bracketed
category that we've been calling
preference priors because I think reason
reason my two sents on this is the
reason why something becomes
pathological as you say in many cases
what we would consider pathological or
maladaptive is very adaptive in certain
contexts so in some ways it's the social
context but it's also the capacity or
the consequence of the individual
reflecting on their own behavior and so
things get worse you know in layman
terms things get worse if you're like oh
this is terrible like why can I not go
to the party why can I not leave my
house without checking the door 15 times
and that seems to me that like what's
What's Happening Here is that you've got
two preference priors fighting with one
another one is one is the higher order
one I would actually say which is I kind
of want to be a normal adaptive socially
functioning human being and the other is
uh there's a very high probability of
there going to be danger and then these
these both kind of feed into the
perceptual Act and the active act so to
speak and so you end up with this
miscalibrated hierarchy where things are
getting confirmed on one level which is
clashing with the confirmation at
another level which makes me think that
there might be some truth in the idea
that a sort of adapted human being is
one where
the the hierarchy is consonant or
compatible the levels are compatible
with each other all the way up so you
don't have something like cognitive
Discord or um yeah this kind of what I
actually been calling opposition or
self-modeling this kind of idea that we
might be sustaining ourselves at one
level but denying evidence at another
level just wondering if you have any
ideas about that and maybe how they
actually feed into the way that we're
perceiving and acting I know it's very
complicated because it's hierarchical so
it's always going to be complicated but
I was wondering if you had any thoughts
about that no I think this is a
wonderful uh explanation that you gave
already I I mean if we try to Now link
it to to uh the am model uh I think it
would be precisely this you I mean you
have in anxiety disorders patients are
aware that their anxiety their
experience is excessive and it's no
useful what they having but they cannot
do anything about it so what they're
feeling is a loss of control I mean
first also about their bily states
because um when you say social anxiety
order they feel that the heart is
Raising that they're sweating they Cann
control the blushing whatsoever this
loss of control actually feeds into
their uh into their feel feeling of uh
of threat of danger of Terror of uh
being humiliated all those negative
emotions so this is one thing the other
thing is also the loss of control that
they're not able to change this part of
themselves so they cannot just update
their belief to say okay but this is
fine or this should be fine um and the
reason could be
um that what what we were saying uh um
when we talked about the preference PRI
you are not able to update them and for
good reason because I mean you should uh
you should learn uh during your early
maturation what the world is like and
you should stick to that because this is
something that is apparently useful and
you shouldn't just update it because you
are in a good mood like you shouldn't
change your preference prior for blood
oxygen if something is interfering uh
with with this kind of mechanisms like
say opiates for example then uh the
system might break and and you might die
the same might also be for this kind of
social preference prior of what social
signals are dangerous and and um so it's
very good that they work very
efficiently without you paying attention
to it in a very autonomic way and even
if you're stupid even if you're drunk or
whatever in this situation you shouldn't
be able to just you know update those
beliefs and and should be uh and bring
yourself into into into
danger great yeah I've got one more
technical question and then then we we
can leave it um I
guess I can't really mentally figure out
whether this is what's the kind of uh
what's the kind of mechanism underlying
this is it because on one hand it sounds
like it's hyper or aberant Precision
over the likelihood distribution and I
think this maps onto something like
hyperfixation or vigilance because the a
is associated with attention and why I
say that is okay so the the the
likelihood is I would you I think it as
why given X so the observation given the
state and let's use our sort of if I've
got a snake phobia if I say that if I
put really high Precision over that
likelihood M Matrix what I'm saying is
these observations I've had is very
likely to have come from the state of
there being a snake MH at the same time
I think of these disorders as being
rooted in the priors I might have a
hyper precise or extremely strong PRI
that I can't be in the company of
snakes and so if I get the slightest
evidence of that given my likelihood
distribution I'm my my posterior is so
Divergent from my prior that that
constitutes prediction error and a call
to
action so there are two kind of
mechanisms going on
there uh and maybe that has actually
been UND depending my sort
of General qualm with the with the
notion of Prior and the ambiguity
surrounding the word prior which I think
has not been really discussed in the
active inference community
enough could you help us see what given
from the perspective of the amydala is
it both is it one of those is it neither
like what's what's kind of going on
here that's a fascinating question and
and uh I mean you you are the first one
to to ask me this kind of question and
and I have to say I also thought about
it I don't have a solution for it I mean
it could have something to do with how
we formulate the active inference model
I think this problem um vanishes if we
use a simpler hierarchical G and filter
for example by Chris matis and uh I
don't know maybe the active inance model
um or C active inflence model got a a
little bit overambitious at some point
and and and is no longer pure in this
very simple computational sense and and
many many things were added to it to um
yeah do many impressive things but maybe
a more vanilla more simple model could
actually also help us to to to figure it
out uh so maybe there is no um no such a
thing uh as a likelihood mapping uh that
is different from uh from prior beliefs
that we should care of oh but I don't
know yeah well not yes I guess no one
know I mean I the the the proof will be
in the the experimental work and the the
triangulation that can come from
experimental work and the neurology and
the neuros scanning and the
computational modeling right um I think
I think what you show very nicely here
is that there's a limit to fear
Rising um and I think I to be honest my
perspective is active inference is
really in its kind of uh it's at its
highest moment of strength when it's
extremely
General so when I say I'm minimizing
variational free energy all the time
yeah like I'm 100% on board with that
right like and and for me that that way
that decomposes into perceptual uh
adequacy and like normative adequacy is
is really nice and the expected free
energy equation is really nice but I
guess these questions is well you're
going to need some deep modeling here I
guess these slight problem is this is
stuff I've run into when I've been
trying to think about these base graphs
and modeling the phenomena that I've
interested in there might be two base
graphs which give you the same
output um so which one wins right is it
just Elegance because we want non-c
complex but accurate models is it
generalizability but you know so these
are open questions but I think they're
really important to raise in this kind
of forum I I totally agree and this was
also the motivation for this kind of uh
paper because at one point we want to
make uh empirical uh predictions I mean
what we what we're doing in this uh in
this paper at the moment is WE Post talk
uh re frame uh uh certain explanations
that we have in the literature and I
mean they're all compatible with with
with the story that we are telling it's
just a new new way of looking at these
things uh but the next step would be of
course we have to I mean we're already
making some kind of empirical
predictions the next will be more
precise computational uh uh predictions
where we really look at uh how it could
be what kind of modeling parameters that
we use are actually reflected by some
changes in the brain or behavior that we
can actually observe uh with the methods
that we have available and then only
then we will see if this model is
actually useful or if it's just a a nice
folk story or something with no
relevance for science whatsoever so this
is what we have to find out and I mean
this is also what I tell uh my my my
colleagues from cognitive Neuroscience
uh who engage now also in active
inference and I tell them yeah
we have to make good predictions
empirical predictions not yet another
modeling paper where uh where we show
show the behavior of some artificial
agent doing something because nowadays
we come to the point that philosophers
are making fun of us they say okay we
are too theoretical we are too detached
from really empirical practice and we
should know get get back to the lab and
and really try so this is definitely the
road map for the future now first that I
conceptualize this kind of um
the the uh space of different phenomena
that we usually like to think think of
when we talk about Thea how it could
actually map to a different narrative
the next will be to come up with a
computational model with uh precise
predictions and then we are going to
test it and I will yeah I haven't
figured out what kind of architecture I
actually um want to
use fantastic fantastic well this is
fascinating I mean the one thing we
didn't even mention are the the
parameters of some involved in
perceptual updating and like the fact
that they contribute um and here you can
sort of have all your linear equations
and stuff but we'll leave that we'll
leave that to the mathematicians and I
also don't think we're going to solve
this problem today I mean there's
there's an important thing that I want
want to say as a a finisher for this for
this last uh uh block because I mean I
said I was so unsure about the laon Bing
and and how the pricee actually sure uh
uh encoded so I mean there's this idea
of you know Cunningham's laws you you
get an answer to your question by uh
posting the the wrong answer to uh to a
question on the internet and this is
what I'm doing now I say okay no no no
there is no such a thing as a likelihood
mapping now go ahead and and show me how
it's really done and the is also applies
to this kind of uh new amca model I
don't know if it's the right model but I
I think we we want wanted to do
something a little bit ambitious because
what we found was that the typical
narrative doesn't add up with what we
observe in the human but also in the
rodent data so I was collaborating with
two mouse researchers and I mean when I
talked to them about my ideas of
effective inflence said yeah this might
be the only way our data could make
sense so there is some some problem with
the existing theory that we having and
maybe um we provided the wrong answer
but I think if somebody's able to
falsify us to to show us where we wrong
I think we will learn a lot of what the
Amal is actually doing this will be what
the next step so yeah excellent well I I
I appreciate both the both the pessimism
and the optimism um um yeah and and
sometimes I just wonder whether it's
just we're just in a semantic cloud of
confusion you know whether if we just
can have different word like I've been
trying to integrate this word autonomous
prior and differentiate it from
something like a a ceptual prior or
hidden State prior and and then I you
know again as I said we need to fold in
stuff like parameters the parameters of
our generative model and linear
functions and the way that this might
spit like the Y given X is really
complicated especially in Dynamic
stochastic worlds um it's not just like
a static hidden varibles so hidden
variables so you're absolutely right I
think I think the money yes I mean
there's this there's this um I think
you're Absol right I mean I don't know
whether humans have the capacity to
model these things perfectly and maybe
we don't need to um science doesn't
necessarily work on perfect modeling it
kind of works on effective predictions
and so maybe we need to get back to the
lab and do a bit more oddly go back to a
bit more of a coar grained World um
where if things work things work I I I
totally agree so uh because I I think
there is no big Narrative of what what
the world really is and there's not one
model to to model the whole world I
think uh and this is uh I think one of
the natural consequences of active
inurance is that we can only go for an
instrumentalised interpretation of what
is going on because anything we observe
is always conditional on something it's
conditional on our model but it's also
conditional on our actions so yeah we
have certain uh we have certain
preferences we want uh we want to
achieve certain things and I mean the
minimal preference could be not to Die
For example and already causes us to
inquire and to act in in a specific way
when we're interacting with the world so
there's always this conditional
dependency that we should uh uh take
under consideration and there is no way
of you know getting the whole joint
distribution it's always conditional on
something so it's always all kinds of
data that we are sampling is sampled for
a particular unit case because that's
thing that's that's perfectly put that's
exactly what I wanted to say but for the
last hour and a half but way better said
Ronnie this was this was amazing I mean
I I you know I oddly expected us to
spend more time talking about the
amigdala and less time talking about
active inference more generally but I
think you're you're one of the you're
one of genuinely you're one of the only
people I know who is teaching active
inference directly on the ground day by
day and I think that is a Hu I mean
there's huge kudos to you because I can
imagine that's not easy especially with
the fact that it's updating the whole
time we have different schema that we're
employing with chucking some ideas out
retaining some simplifying complexifying
so thanks for doing that rather you than
me I guess I'm doing that in part here
um will be much worse but yeah no thank
you so much this was incredibly useful I
again I leave all of these conversations
often times just to touch more confused
than when started but I think that's a
good Socratic sign that we're making
progress um I always ask our our guests
where can people find you I'm sure
people are going to have lots of
questions the amigdalar is a kind of
permanent object of Fascination for
people so if they wanted to ask
questions or find out about the courses
you're running where can people reach
out to you so my uh blue sky and Twitter
handle is sweet
nuron and uh you can also find my
website sweet neuron
doat yeah and I mean I also like to say
that I really loved uh talking to you
even forgot this is uh recorded here
because I mean I got so much in my in my
head space and and talking about those
interesting things so yeah I I love this
format I Love Your Way of of doing it
and it was truly an inspiring and
thought-provoking um discussion oh
you're very kind you're very kind I
think that might be the best send off
I've had I'm gonna I'm gonna that's
that's made my day uh excellent Ronnie
it's been an absolute treat I've learned
a lot I'm confused like last week I'm
going to go take a nap
um thank you so much for joining me
again thank you for me and The Institute
thanks for hosting this